<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Binary Adages - learning</title><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/feeds/learning.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://rayalan.github.io/</id><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>An Interview Catastrophe</title><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/low-energy-interview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alan Ray</name></author><id>tag:rayalan.github.io,2024-07-22:/low-energy-interview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You came across as low energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective employer&amp;rsquo;s feedback, not entirely appreciated by me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve certainly had my fair share of catastrophic interviews. The one where I mixed up whether the company used PHP or Perl. The lunch from which any …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You came across as low energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective employer&amp;rsquo;s feedback, not entirely appreciated by me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve certainly had my fair share of catastrophic interviews. The one where I mixed up whether the company used PHP or Perl. The lunch from which any testimony would have convicted my prospective employer of just about any &lt;a href="https://www.eeoc.gov/"&gt;EEOC&lt;/a&gt; lawsuit. The one where my would-be boss challenged the technical merit of the approach I&amp;rsquo;d co-designed and developed to handle complex radio routing requirements in life-and-death situations&lt;sup id="fnref:police"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:police"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But being told I might not have enough energy for the job&amp;hellip;that hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was tempted, of course, to just blow it off. And that might be the right answer. But as a teacher of mine once said, failure hurts, so you might as well squeeze every possible lesson out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of why the feedback stings is because it ties into what I know is a weakness &amp;ndash; figuring out how to make the right first impression, the juggling act between confidence and arrogance, between listening well and giving answers in a time-limited scenario, showing appropriate interest while recognizing that the interview process is about discovering and evaluating unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in this interview, I&amp;rsquo;d thought I&amp;rsquo;d found a balance of those traits that was really me and a good fit for the situation&amp;hellip;only to get completely rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-interview"&gt;The interview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did it all start? An acquaintance, Bob, who knew I was looking for a job, reached out. He had some openings and wanted to know if I might be interested. Our conversation went well, and I was invited out to see the company and see if there might be a fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was all very informal. There was no job description, no hiring manager or recruiter, no details about the company other than what was publicly available. &amp;ldquo;Just&amp;rdquo; a chance to come in and chat&lt;sup id="fnref:technical"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:technical"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the company, I met Bob and Bob&amp;rsquo;s boss Charles. I&amp;rsquo;d carefully prepared to listen, to learn about what the company needed, and to see where there might be good synergy between my skills and their needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;So what do you want to do for the company?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles asked that question a few minutes into the conversation. I had no idea; after all, that was supposed to be the whole point of the casual conversation? I tried to gently and diplomatically bounce the question back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Part of why I&amp;rsquo;m here is to figure out what would make a great opportunity for both of us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, I tried to say something to that effect. Let&amp;rsquo;s leave whether or not I was exactly that quick thinking on my feet to the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles was not happy, at least according to his body language. I tried to engage him and draw him out &amp;ndash; at least as well as I could while he and Bob were driving the interview questions. But Charles&amp;rsquo;s body language continued to be hostile and disengaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after perhaps half an hour, that was the interview. There was nothing casual or low-key about the conversation. Charles came across as hurried. He or Bob drove the conversation the whole time, and my efforts to create a back-and-forth exchange fell spectacularly flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not surprised I didn&amp;rsquo;t get an offer, but being described as low energy surprised me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the downsides of interviews is they are all special snowflakes. But here are a few of the takeaways that I&amp;rsquo;ve mulled over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Win&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Going in with a loose game plan to listen and find mutual wins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to make detailed plans. I like to know exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m getting into. I like having three or four contingency plans. Even though it worked out terribly in this scenario, I think going in with goals, some prepared questions to help me get to those goals, and the right mindset was the right approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Win&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Letting the company drive the interview.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the interview advice I&amp;rsquo;ve heard more or less suggests that candidates take over the interview and run it. I have friends who can &amp;ndash; and have &amp;ndash; pulled that off in interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I find it disrespectful, especially when companies usually have crafted the interview process for their own evaluation process. I&amp;rsquo;ve rarely seen it done well in interviews when I&amp;rsquo;m the interviewer. Even though there was clearly more latitude here with a more informal process, I still don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s respectful to snatch control of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Win&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Being prepared to drive the conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went in well prepared, if an opening was presented, to lead the conversation in learning what a win-win scenario might look like. I feel good about trying to establish a back-and-forth exchange within the confines of the interview format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Not openly (re)setting expectations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I wish I had stopped a bit into the interview and said something like. &amp;ldquo;Bob, Charles, can we step back for a moment? My understanding is that I&amp;rsquo;m here so we can have a casual conversation about whether there&amp;rsquo;s a position that would be a win-win scenario for both of us. Is that your understanding?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what Charles was told. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what Bob thought he&amp;rsquo;d told me. But it seems really likely that expectations were mismatched, and I wish I&amp;rsquo;d been quick thinking enough to have tried to make sure we were on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Not openly setting expectations before the visit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, a good presentation consists of:
* Telling them what you are going to tell them.
* Telling them.
* Telling them what you&amp;rsquo;ve told them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of value in having a clear goal for any meeting, and I ponder if I should have dropped Bob a note a day or two before my meeting said something like, &amp;ldquo;Looking forward to getting together. In my mind, we&amp;rsquo;re casually chatting to see if there&amp;rsquo;s a win-win opportunity as well as doing some technical evaluation. Does that sound right?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it would have helped, but it might have made sure at least Bob and I were on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Musing&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Maybe energy wasn&amp;rsquo;t the issue.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After mulling it over, I&amp;rsquo;m not entirely sure how to interpret Bob&amp;rsquo;s low energy comment. There&amp;rsquo;s the straight-forward interpretation &amp;ndash; I didn&amp;rsquo;t come across as engaged during the interview. And that might be true, especially since I know I was trying to parse Charles&amp;rsquo;s lack of engagement and figure out how to adjust. But I also ponder a couple other interpretations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charles doesn&amp;rsquo;t like you, and the easiest way to describe his dislike is &amp;ldquo;low energy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; Totally fair; it was pretty clear that Charles and I would be at least something of an acquired taste for each other. And depending on how aware Bob was of Charles&amp;rsquo;s reaction and how openly Bob can speak about it, maybe &amp;ldquo;low energy&amp;rdquo; is as close as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We want employees who are really enthusiastic about the opportunity, even before they know anything about it.&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve run into this in other interviews &amp;ndash; employers often want people to be very excited about the opportunity before they&amp;rsquo;ve said much. In contrast, I tend to be very aware of how much is unknown and respond with cautious optimism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="so-what"&gt;So what&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final thought is that, while it&amp;rsquo;s great to wring as many lessons as possible from failure &amp;ndash; and preferably the failure of others, because it is a whole lot less painful than going through it myself &amp;ndash; at the end of the day, interviews can&amp;rsquo;t be taken too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost by definition, everyone has more losses than wins when it comes to interviewing: You keep interviewing until you take a job. And for all that one tries to put their best foot forward, so much can go wrong that is totally not under one&amp;rsquo;s control. Sometimes people won&amp;rsquo;t understand you, and that&amp;rsquo;s okay. Learn to get a good laugh out of it &amp;ndash; or at least a blog article &amp;ndash; and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? What lessons would you have taken away from such an interview?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:police"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were police radios, and officers relied on what I&amp;rsquo;d done to be able to talk reliably to different responders and agencies in a wide variety of scenarios. Sometimes, for example, they needed to temporarily switch channels and then have the radio automatically switch back in a few seconds, unless there was a manual request to switch to a different channel. The requirements for stitching together multiple incompatible radio systems were&amp;hellip;special.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:police" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:technical"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point during my visit, there was also some time set aside for a technical evaluation. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember if that was explicitly stated before the visit or not, but I&amp;rsquo;d certainly anticipated that happening. When chatting about the interview results, the company&amp;rsquo;s feedback was that I&amp;rsquo;d nailed it technically (and that was my own assessment as well), so I&amp;rsquo;ve omitted the technical aspect of the interview as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem relevant.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:technical" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="learning"></category><category term="user experience"></category><category term="process"></category><category term="experiences"></category><category term="failures"></category></entry></feed>