<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Binary Adages - systems</title><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/feeds/systems.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://rayalan.github.io/</id><updated>2024-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Annual Performance Reviews (Part 2)</title><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/annual-reviews-part-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Alan Ray</name></author><id>tag:rayalan.github.io,2024-01-29:/annual-reviews-part-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last time, I wrote about &lt;a href="https://rayalan.github.io/annual-reviews.html"&gt;the problem of annual reviews&lt;/a&gt; and started rethinking the problem if we were solving it for the first time with modern technology. By the end of the thought experiment, we were a company designing a new product, SmartReviews, with four key features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular, low-effort collection …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last time, I wrote about &lt;a href="https://rayalan.github.io/annual-reviews.html"&gt;the problem of annual reviews&lt;/a&gt; and started rethinking the problem if we were solving it for the first time with modern technology. By the end of the thought experiment, we were a company designing a new product, SmartReviews, with four key features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular, low-effort collection of feedback from employees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trend-based alerting for management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Directed prompts for specific feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI-assisted writing (because everything is cooler with AI).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I want to go through each of these features in detail, exploring how they streamline the annual performance review process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would each of these features work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="low-effort-feedback-collection"&gt;Low-effort feedback collection&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the places I&amp;rsquo;ve worked, feedback collection is hard. Every few months, I&amp;rsquo;m asked to give feedback on some people. But do I remember specifics? Was I paying particular attention to their work? Often, I have this bland &amp;ldquo;they were a good employee &amp;ndash; what else do I say?&amp;rdquo; reaction. Meanwhile, there are employees who I have very clear praise or insight about, and I&amp;rsquo;m not prompted to submit any feedback there. Sure, I could go the extra mile to do so&amp;hellip;but the system doesn&amp;rsquo;t make it easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SmartReviews would solve this by being tied into all the systems. It would look at tickets, pull requests, emails, instant messages, documents, and calendars to see who had been interacting. And then it would prompt each individual for notes or observations about those interactions. It&amp;rsquo;d provide handy links to the relevant artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback could either be one of two types:
  * &lt;em&gt;An observation point&lt;/em&gt;: When Jane did such-n-such, it came across as unprofessional because of this-n-that.
  * &lt;em&gt;A hypothesis of a trend&lt;/em&gt;: I suspect that when Joe is frustrated, he expects others to solve his problem, leading him to post terse messages in Slack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, the feedback wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be shared. The goal is collecting feedback; it will be synthesized later. The goal is to help people understand long-term trends. Individuals are prompted for feedback every couple weeks&lt;sup id="fnref:tune"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:tune"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; based on their interactions with others &amp;ndash; and, of course, they can make notes about other people. For trends, the individual is prompted if they&amp;rsquo;ve had any noteworthy interactions. Was the hypothesis supported? Or was there a conflicting example?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus to SmartReviews &amp;ndash; we can roughly track how much time people are spending on feedback, which artifacts people reference, and how helpful that feedback is to individuals. Because we sell this product to lots of companies, we can see how different designs of our software lead to different outcomes, and select the best review processes&lt;sup id="fnref:privacy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:privacy"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then when the actual review period rolls around, each employee has all of these pre-populated data points on each employee, along with any hypotheses they created about bigger behavior patterns. Now it is clear who should be writing reviews for whom, based on what each employee observed over the past months. An employee can look over lots of individual interactions and ask, &amp;ldquo;What broader pattern emerges?&amp;rdquo; Or an employee can revisit a hypothesis, see if it was supported by the evidence, and refine or abandon it as necessary. Since all of this feedback was initially created in the context of artifacts such as messages, calendar appointments, and pull requests, reviewers don&amp;rsquo;t need to go hunting for that data &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s already included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, we can give employees some help writing reviews with AI (see that feature later on) to further streamline this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="trend-based-alerting-for-management"&gt;Trend-based alerting for management&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, review systems want everyone to get reviewed. Often, this means someone gets asked to write a review about Joe who is a complete loner, and it&amp;rsquo;s really hard to know what to say. Joe wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem. But nobody really knows what Joe did. And so Joe&amp;rsquo;s review is very bland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With SmartReviews, this problem can be spotted during the year, without waiting until the review period rolls around. SmartReviews can look at which individuals aren&amp;rsquo;t generating any feedback &amp;ndash; or generating lots of negative feedback &amp;ndash; and alert managers to problematic trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the managers aren&amp;rsquo;t getting specific feedback from SmartReview &amp;ndash; the effectiveness of our system hinges on users knowing that their individual observations are private until they share them. But we can do an aggregate analysis and alert managers that they may need to pay more attention in a particular area&lt;sup id="fnref:scale"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:scale"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="directed-prompts-for-specific-feedback"&gt;Directed prompts for specific feedback&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to collecting feedback from individuals, SmartReviews can give directed prompts to people who interact with a certain person. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You recently read some documentation [link]. How would you evaluate it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These prompts can have a variety of sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individuals wanting to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers looking for feedback about a specific habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System owners looking for feedback about their systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an advanced feature, SmartReview could use sentiment analysis to generate smart prompts. For example, if one individual is giving a lot of negative feedback about a particular system, it might generate a prompt for other users of the system, specifically soliciting their experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="ai-assisted-writing"&gt;AI-assisted writing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, writing reviews is hard. What&amp;rsquo;s hard about them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s hard to have anything concrete. The person is a generic good employee. They work hard, communicate decently, and ship quality code. It&amp;rsquo;s good work. There&amp;rsquo;s not much to critique. But there&amp;rsquo;s also not many specifics to praise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get the tone right. I want this feedback to be taken as a strong trait that could get stronger, not as a weakness. I really want some other feedback to be taken as a long-term concern, but not an immediate problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both these cases, we can introduce an AI-assisted review assistant (ARA). For good employees, ARA can understand the characteristics that make a good employee. Then ARA can give prompts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often have you observed this behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When is a time when they illustrated this behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you ever seen them not exhibit this behavior?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By asking these questions, ARA can help draw out and help construct a far better review than &amp;ldquo;I really like Jane&amp;rsquo;s work.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, when I&amp;rsquo;m just frustrated, I can enter my rant into ARA, and ARA can help me turn that into helpful feedback:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prompt for more details (as above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prompt for other considerations, such as what the employee has done well (as above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help me understand how the feedback is likely to be received. &amp;ldquo;This feedback is likely to be seen as an unprofessional personal conflict because of these factors&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand how I want to categorize my feedback (praise, possible long-term concern, growth opportunity, immediately problematic behavior).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite my review with a professional tone, according to my intent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterate on the above feedback until I&amp;rsquo;ve generated some professional and helpful feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature is hard to get right (AI hallucinations could be all sorts of headaches), but it could also really help feedback to be shared with the right context. As an added bonus, since we&amp;rsquo;re dealing in a closed system (both the employees and managers are using SmartReview), we can add some tags or other metadata to help indicate the intent of the feedback, which can help everyone be on the same page when they read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="so-what"&gt;So what&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we&amp;rsquo;ve got a system that is really cool:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a minimal hassle when reviews come around; most of the reviews are being generated in real time on an ongoing basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feedback is being given based on actual interactions, not based on who is selected to give reviews.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers can be aware in real time of problems or employees who may not be interacting. In particular, the system may be able to surface scenarios where everyone is struggling, but each individual thinks it is just them that is struggling, and thus nobody is speaking up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system still integrates into a traditional annual or semi-annual review cycle. (This characteristic is important for adoption of our new product.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is visibility into how much time and effort goes into generating feedback. Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to close the loop on that feedback and whether it was helpful or worth the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It won&amp;rsquo;t do everything &amp;ndash; it won&amp;rsquo;t, for example, force employees to give feedback or change a company culture where open feedback isn&amp;rsquo;t welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it follows the DevOps principle of &amp;ldquo;that which is done often is done well&amp;rdquo; and turns feedback from a irregular activity into a regularly recurring activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think &amp;ndash; is this a good modernization of the annual review process? What else could SmartReview do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:tune"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can tune the frequency based on what gets the best responses.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:tune" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:privacy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will need to be very clear with users about which data will be visible just to SmartReviews as a company to make the product better vs. which data will be visible to others. Telling SmartReviews &amp;ldquo;this feedback wasn&amp;rsquo;t helpful&amp;rdquo; is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than telling a co-worker &amp;ldquo;this feedback wasn&amp;rsquo;t helpful.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:privacy" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:scale"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help employees feel comfortable with their individual observations being used as sentiment, we might introduce a perspective for negative feedback. For example, Jane generating a lot of feedback about how they can grow is very different than Joe generating lots of feedback about how they are creating a hostile work environment.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:scale" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="systems"></category><category term="brainstorming"></category></entry><entry><title>Annual Performance Reviews (Part 1)</title><link href="https://rayalan.github.io/annual-reviews.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Alan Ray</name></author><id>tag:rayalan.github.io,2024-01-15:/annual-reviews.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Annual performance reviews are one of those staples of American corporations. As far as I can tell, they haven&amp;rsquo;t changed much in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they&amp;rsquo;re done semiannually. More recently it&amp;rsquo;s popular to do the &amp;ldquo;360-degree&amp;rdquo; reviews to get feedback from peers and direct reports, not just one …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Annual performance reviews are one of those staples of American corporations. As far as I can tell, they haven&amp;rsquo;t changed much in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes they&amp;rsquo;re done semiannually. More recently it&amp;rsquo;s popular to do the &amp;ldquo;360-degree&amp;rdquo; reviews to get feedback from peers and direct reports, not just one&amp;rsquo;s boss. They&amp;rsquo;re typically linked to compensation adjustments and promotions. Occasionally, they&amp;rsquo;re integrated with practices such as &lt;a href="https://insight.kellogg.northwestern.edu/article/performance-review-ranking-system-best"&gt;stack ratings&lt;/a&gt;, making it easy for employers to cull the &amp;ldquo;bottom&amp;rdquo; performers&lt;sup id="fnref:mystery"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:mystery"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we do better than the traditional performance review?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, they often cause a massive amount of work for people in writing reviews. Worse yet, that work often seems disproportional to the benefit. I mean, when was the last time someone wrote &amp;ldquo;writes great performance reviews&amp;rdquo; in their review of someone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with decades of corporate experience, the modern internet, and a bit of thought, can we do better than the traditional performance review?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-goal"&gt;The goal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is often the case, it&amp;rsquo;s worth asking &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the purpose of performance reviews?&amp;rdquo; Or perhaps better yet: &amp;ldquo;What should the purpose of performance reviews be?&amp;rdquo; I find companies often have a multitude of goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formally document unofficial sentiment. Everyone knows Jane has been doing a good job, but the review gives a way to document it and acknowledge it at a corporate level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give valuable feedback for employees to grow and learn from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See the forest for the trees. Periodic reviews can be a chance to look at trends and patterns, not just individual moments. This helps us avoid the fallacies such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallacy_of_composition"&gt;composition&lt;/a&gt;, looking instead of whether the sum of the many moments is more &amp;ndash; or perhaps less &amp;ndash; than the individual moments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Force managers to give feedback. Ideally, of course, an employee knows at all times what is thought of their performance, especially with regard to their boss. But sometimes that communication doesn&amp;rsquo;t go very well for whatever reason, and formal reviews force feedback to at least at some frequency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-struggles"&gt;The struggles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At their worst, employee reviews become a performative dance where the question of &amp;ldquo;How much does my boss like me?&amp;rdquo; gets translated in a corporate justification. If the employee is liked, then corresponding weight is given to the employee&amp;rsquo;s accolades. A disliked employee finds more attention given to their shortcomings. And given the complexity of software development, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to justify either perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to say this; it&amp;rsquo;s the stuff of law suits and HR nightmares. But it can be really easy to create a review system that sanitizes the manager&amp;rsquo;s opinion rather than giving real feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else can go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many (most?) people aren&amp;rsquo;t good at tracking trends over time. This gives many reviews a heavy recency bias. (And there&amp;rsquo;s often very little training on this topic.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people lack the full picture when they give feedback. For example, suppose I notice that John seems courteous but distant when I interact with him. Is that because he&amp;rsquo;s busy prioritizing more important work? Is that because he doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to help me more? Is that because he has a different baseline for what friendly looks like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are often implicitly pressured not to give critical feedback. People may avoid high-quality criticism for a number of reasons, from a fear of feedback being blown out of proportion in the review to a fear of breaking social expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;360-style reviews often allow employees to choose their peer reviewers. Given the impact reviews can have on performance and compensation, there&amp;rsquo;s heavy incentive to select those who seem most likely to give a positive review &amp;ndash; not necessarily those who will give the most thoughtful feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-ideal-systems"&gt;The ideal system(s)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine we&amp;rsquo;re starting a new company that is recreating performance reviews from scratch. We want to create a product &amp;ndash; and a system of reviews &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s tailored to the modern business world. What would would we want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a business owner, I want a way to formally document performance that informs compensation adjustments and promotions&lt;sup id="fnref:departures"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:departures"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so that quality employees are appropriately recognized and legal entanglements are avoided.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a business owner, I want my managers to have timely and relevant feedback so they can make good decisions around employee growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a manager, I want reviews to be straightforward and low hassle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an employee, I want my review to highlight my strengths and best work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an employee, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be surprised by negative feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an employee, I want a chance to correct negative perceptions before they influence my annual review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a company selling this product, I want there to be a simple transition path for new customers from their current system so that we can gain customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a company selling this product, I want our product to be profitable so that I make a profit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a company selling this product, I want companies to stick with my product so that I&amp;rsquo;m confident the product is at least good enough to retain its current users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the challenge is that different parts of the system have different goals. Managers would like to know everything as soon as possible, but employees often don&amp;rsquo;t want to prematurely escalate concerns. As someone giving feedback, I want my experience to be taken seriously. But as someone receiving feedback, I don&amp;rsquo;t want a single person&amp;rsquo;s critique to unfairly dominate my review. And with each company and individual having their own style for how quickly and vocally to speak about issues, conflicting objectives easily arise, such as a manager wanting faster feedback, but individuals wanting to give more time for patterns to play out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a company wanting to sell a product, we&amp;rsquo;d prefer to develop a product that is culture agnostic. Not only does this approach give us a broader customer base, but changing company culture is a hard problem &amp;ndash; and it&amp;rsquo;s far more complex if we&amp;rsquo;re selling a review system paired with a particular cultural approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-product"&gt;The product&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what might our product do? Let&amp;rsquo;s give it a set of features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular, low-effort collection of feedback from employees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trend-based alerting for management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Directed prompts for specific feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI-assisted writing (because everything is cooler with AI).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s call our product SmartReviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time, in &lt;a href="https://rayalan.github.io/annual-reviews-part-2.html"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ll unpack more of my ideas of how these features would work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:mystery"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stack rankings seem like a terrible idea because one is incentivized to be the best person on a terrible team. I&amp;rsquo;m sure that there is more to it than that, but a bit of marketing to make the upsides more obvious would go a long way. After all, engineers are generally known for understanding complex systems and problem solving; does one really want them gaming the performance evaluation system?&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:mystery" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:departures"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when employees need to be let go, the business wants a documentation trail that avoids lawsuits and similar unpleasantness.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:departures" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="systems"></category><category term="brainstorming"></category></entry></feed>